Dos Passos mss., 1903-1950 LMC 1283
Lilly Library
Dos Passos mss.
1903-1950
Lilly Library
Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970
Gordon, James Riely, 1863-1937
LMC 1283
1 Box
The Dos Passos mss., 1903-1950, consists of letters and college writings of author John Dos Passos, 1896-1970, and legal files and correspondence of his family in connection with the estate of his father John Randolph Dos Passos, 1844-1917.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
John Dos Passos, 1896-1970, was an American writer of the post-World War I "Lost Generation." He was born in Chicago, Illinois on January 14, 1896 as the illegitimate son of John Randolph Dos Passos (1844–1917) and Lucy Addison Sprigg Madison. He attended Harvard College from 1912-1916, where he developed an interest in writing. During World War I, he worked as an ambulance driver in France before joining the U.S. Army Medical Corps. He based his first novel, One Man's Initiation: 1917 (published in 1920) on his experiences during the war. In 1921, he published another anti-war novel: Three Soldiers. However, Dos Passos is most famous for his U.S.A trilogy. Published as three separate novels, The 42nd Parallel (1930), 1919 (1932), and The Big Money (1936), the trilogy explores the culture of early 20th century America using experimental techniques. In addition to writing novels, Dos Passos was also an avid traveler, artist, and political writer, though his political views shifted dramatically over the course of his life. He died in Baltimore, Maryland on September 28, 1970.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1980
Scope and Content Note
The letters from John Dos Passos are primarily to his aunt, Mary Lucy (Dos Passos) Gordon, (Mrs. James Riely Gordon), although a few others are present as well. The writings are papers for a Harvard English class, 1912-1913. Also included is an unpublished novel written as a class project, Afterglow, and the original autograph manuscript of his first published work Against American Literature (New Republic, Oct. 14, 1916). The legal files are chiefly those of James Riely Gordon and his wife, Mary Lucy (Dos Passos) Gordon, concerned with the estate and law suits by and against it, of John Dos Passos, Sr.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Authors, American; Authors, American--20th century--Biography; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970 --Correspondence.; Dos Passos, John R. (John Randolph), 1844-1917.
- Correspondence., 1903-1920
- Correspondence., 1921-1930
- Correspondence., 1931-1950
- Chronology and Testimony., Aug. 5, 1916-Oct. 10, 1924
- Writings: Afterglow. Harvard (I), [1915?]
- Writings: Afterglow. Harvard (II), [1915?]; (carbon)
- Writings: Afterglow. Harvard, [1915?]; (photocopy)
- Writings: Freshman themes. Harvard English class assignments., Dec. 1912-1913
- Writings: Freshman themes. Harvard English class assignments., Dec. 1912-1913; (photocopy)
- Writings: A Meadow of Tall Grass. (I)
- Writings: A Meadow of Tall Grass. (II)
- Writings: A Meadow of Tall Grass. (I), (photocopies)
- Writings: A Meadow of Tall Grass. (II), (photocopies)
- Miscellaneous envelopes with clipping
- Writings: Against American Literature., Ca. 1916
- Legal: transcript, pp. 1-183., Mar. 27, 1944
- Legal: transcript, pp. 184-416., Mar. 27, 1944
- Legal: transcript, pp. 417-596., Mar. 27, 1944
- Legal: transcript, pp. 597-800., Mar. 27, 1944
- Legal: transcript, pp. 801-1022., Mar. 27, 1944
- Legal: transcript, pp. 1001-1197., Mar. 27, 1944
  General
  (p. 1150 missing)
- Legal correspondence., 1917-1926
- Powers of attorney made (and revoked) by John Dos Passos., 1917-1940
- First account of executors., 1924
- Supplemental account of the executors and litigation., 1924-1926
- Pilgrim Mining Properties., 1938-1939
- Legal correspondence., 1941-1943
- John Dos Passos v. Mary L. Gordon, et al., 1941-1942
- Byron Ralston personal misc.
- Miscellaneous
- Deeds., 1892-1926; (copies)
- Sandy Point Corp. correspondence., 1926-1940
- Sale of Sandy Point Farm(s)., 1926
- Sandy Point Farms foreclosure., 1938
- Sandy Point Farm(s) - sale(s), 1937-1943; undated